CHAPTER 10

Slavery and the Seascapes of Danish
Slave Trade from Tranquebar
to Kedah, Aceh, Colombo,
Cape Town, Mauritius and
Denmark, 1632-1790

In 1618 the Danish East India Company sent its first expedition and the Danes reached Tranquebar on the Coromandel Coast in 1620. After obtaining permission from Raghunatha Nayak (1600-34) the ruler of Thanjavur, a trading settlement was established in 1624.1 It served as the headquarters for Danish trade in Asia.

Jon Olafsson the Danish traveller came to Tranquebar and he stayed there during 1624-5. He had mentioned that he had a Hindu servant boy who was 15 years old. The Portuguese missionaries in the Danish settlement had baptized him and the boy embraced Christianity. It is unclear whether the boy was a domestic slave or not. Olafsson said that the Catholic missionaries had the habit of baptizing many individuals like this. They had also purchased children from their parents and brought them close to God.2

The Danes in Tranquebar faced difficulties for conducting their overseas trade because of the participation of Denmark in the Thirty Years War in Europe. It led to the decline of shipping and commerce between Copenhagen and Tranquebar and so the Danes conducted trade from the port of Masulipatnam on the Telugu Coast in 1625.3 There had been no commercial traffic between Copenhagen and Tranquebar between 1639 and 1668.4 The Danes searched for prospects of commerce within Asian ports and began to trade with Banten in Java from Tranquebar between 1645 and 1662.

THE BEGINNINGS OF THE DANISH SLAVE
TRADE IN TRANQUEBAR, 1632

Danish records mention the distinction between white men and slavery. They also differentiate between Negro slaves and the Tamil slaves in Tranquebar. Mads Rasmussen in his diary mentioned on 17 March 1632 that the Danes could get 200 Tamil slaves at Tranquebar and they were sent in the sailing vessels of Tranquebar which paid customs duty at the port. The Danes purchased slaves who were available and used them for domestic work. Some of the families who were made captives during the wars were also sold. Thus, various social conditions that prevailed permitted them to enter into slavery.5 Brendt Pessart, the Danish Governor of Tranqubar (1636-44) had purchased slaves for domestic use.6

Some Portuguese traders came from Nagapattinam and settled in the Danish settlement. Joao Pinto the Portuguese renegade, became a resident of Tranquebar and came forward to offer help to the Danish company as a sailor by flying the Danish flag in the ships.7 It had been reported in May 1639 that he extended the offer to ships for sailing to Melaka. Andrew Cogan, the English scribe in Madras reported this matter to the Agents and Council of Masulipatnam. He wondered that how this offer was taken seriously into consideration by the Portuguese Viceroy in Goa and also as to the conditions laid out in this scheme which remained secret and largely unknown.8

It is found in Spanish records that in Tranquebar the Danes had sent a ship that reached the Philippines. The permission to anchor the Danish ship called Buena Esperanza in Manila had created a furore. The issue was raised in 1645. Two royal decrees were issued in this connection to the port officials in Manila. It condemned the decision of the Spanish colonial authorities.9

THE PRIVATE TRADERS IN TRANQUEBAR AND
THE GROWTH OF SLAVE TRADE OF THE DANISH
COMPANY WITH THE PORT OF KEDAH AND
ACEH IN SUMATRA IN SOUTH EAST ASIA, 1646-1647

Wilhelm Leyel (1644-54) became the Danish Governor of Tranquebar in 1644. He felt that slave trade was a means to obtain quick profits, which could then be used for gifts, tributes and outstanding debts. The Danish Company in particular sold the crews of Bengali ships, which they had seized as prize. Slave trade was widespread at that time on the Tamil Coast and the Portuguese and the Dutch had indulged in it. Leyel in his letter dated 21 September 1646, gave instructions to Hans Ekman the captain of the ship and stated that 38 slaves (both Muslims and Hindus) could be offered as gifts to the king in Kedah to develop Danish trade contacts.10 It is known that the Danes felt the need for commercial intermediaries in order to develop trade and in 1645 the company in Tranquebar entrusted all its affairs in Kedah to a Tamil agent.

A letter from Leyel the Danish Governor dated 19 February 1647 to Jörgen Hansen, the captain of the ship called Christianshavn, mentioned that if Ismail Nayinar the business partner of Leyel brought slaves onboard, they should be considered Leyel’s property. In the same letter, he also discussed as to how to procure provisions for the use of slaves on board.11 Thus one finds Leyel the Danish Governor was himself a slave owner and it proves that slave trading also took place among the officials of the Danish Company.

It is found amongst the records of Wilhelm Leyel that slaves passed through the port of Tranquebar as commodities.12 Slaves were purchased and sold locally and they were exported to the market in Aceh. This slave trade was of particular importance for the Danes at Tranquebar during the period when the Danish Company was under pressure at home and could not send ships to India during the Thirty Years War. A mention has been found that William Leyel had transported 8 slaves in August 1647, 165 slaves in September 1647 and 20 slaves in October 1647. Thus the total of 193 slaves had been purchased and sent making him a successful slave trader.13

The Portuguese continued to migrate from Nagapattinam and settle in the nearby port of Tranquebar. Leyel the Danish Governor therefore permitted the construction of a new Catholic church at Tranquebar in 1646. With the capture of Nagapattinam by the Dutch in 1658, a huge population of the Portuguese sought asylum under the Danes.

Mourids Christensen the Danish official in his diary entry dated 16 March 1671, had reported that the company in Tranquebar purchased and sold Tamil slaves like animals or cargo. The natives who were in need of food, sold their sons and daughters. Men and women slaves thus came to be employed on a large scale.14

The Danes established trading contacts with Aceh in Sumatra in 1694. It was at that time they allowed export of slaves in the ships of the Tamil merchants.15 Missionary records mention that the marakkayars, the Tamil Muslims from Tranquebar and Poriayar, played a significant role in the trade and traffic of the Danish shipping with slaves and textiles to Aceh.16

The Danish trade in slaves from Tranquebar developed because the company ships took slave cargoes to Aceh. Many of the slaves transported were debt slaves who could not pay and clear their debts. Also there were slaves who were not able to meet their household expenses and therefore sold themselves and their children. Thus, the number of slaves available depended on the local conditions in Tranquebar. It is known from records that the year 1696 was said to be a good year when plenty of slaves were available. The year 1698 had been a bad one in terms of the scarcity of slaves.17

A second Danish East India Company was formed in 1670. The capital for trade came much later only in 1696 when two Danish ships arrived from Copenhagen to Tranquebar.18 Tranquebar had capital for investment and steady slave trade continued till the end of the seventeenth century. Traders had to pay customs duty for shipping slaves to the Danish Company which had been earlier reorganized in 1668. The trade prospered between 1687 and 1704. When the Second Danish East India Company was dissolved and replaced by the Danish Asiatic Company in 1732, it was decided that the trade in slaves was permissible only as company trade banning the export of slaves by private traders.

THE SYSTEM OF SLAVERY IN TRANQUEBAR
AND NOTICES OF THE LUTHERAN
MISSIONARIES AFTER THEIR ARRIVAL

The predominance of the household economy was a major element in Danish slavery practices at Tranquebar. This was influenced more by existing local patterns. The productive activities of slaves in Tranquebar before the arrival of Danes, came to be integrated and continued to be followed with the domestic or household realm of their owners.

The Lutheran missionaries who arrived at Tranquebar in 1706 noticed the three types of slaves particularly referring to three groups of people like the Tamils, Portuguese and Muslims. On arrival in Tranquebar, Barholomäus Ziegenbalg wrote a letter to Francke on 25 September 1706 in which he suggested that the Danish Halle mission should be kick started by purchase of slaves, who should be forced to be converted to Protestantism.19 He said that this would not be un-Christian behaviour because the parents in Tranquebar had faced financial difficulties and so they had been regularly selling their children to make ends meet.

After staying four years in Tranquebar, Ziegenbalg came to explain about slavery in his letter to Francke dated 23 December 1710. He mentioned that since the parents in Tranquebar had wished to sell their children as slaves, it would not be wrong to buy them oneself for a small amount of money so that they could be converted and brought to the fold of Protestant Church. He added that the missionaries had purchased two such slave children and they studied in the missionary school where the kids were doing well. The parents had in the meanwhile had also become Christians.20 Ziegenbalg wrote that this was one type of slaves in Tranquebar, who spoke Tamil language and whose form of bondage did not remove them completely from their family and background, whose condition of servitude might also not be permanent and whose own offspring would not automatically become slaves as per the local custom.

Ziegenbalg continued to write in detail about slavery and he said that there was another type of slaves who were of Indo-Portuguese parentage. They spoke Portuguese language and often served as household servants. Many of them were Catholics who had been educated or converted by the Portuguese missionaries, who had come earlier to Tranquebar before the arrival of the Protestants. Here again the degree of servitude and the dividing lines between servant, serf, and slave varied, were different and negotiable and slavery was not something that could be set apart from debt-related, contractual and more voluntary forms of master-servant relationships in absolute terms.

Ziegenbalg who noticed the society carefully said that there was an important category of slaves who were of native low castes. This third social group of slaves served in the Portuguese households as domestic servants. He stated that the catechist Rayanayakkan belonged to this category and he belonged to the paraiyar caste.21

Ziegenbalg added that another category of slaves in Tranquebar were the Muslim prisoners sold by their captors. They were converted to Islam forcefully. He said that the slaves were brought to Tranquebar from neighbouring places for sale by slave traders.22

It is very clear that the Lutheran missionaries in Tranquebar did not reject slavery in all possible varieties. They wished to purchase slaves of certain categories for their own use, as they considered this to be necessary being local cultural understandings of servitude and of the way in which servants were attached to masters and households. The slaves constituted an important proportion of missionary converts. These slaves were educated in missionary school and remained slaves even after baptism.

SLAVES IN TRANQUEBAR AND THEIR CONVERSION
TO CHRISTIANITY UNDER THE LUTHERAN
MISSIONARIES, 1707-1708

The register of baptism maintained by the Lutheran missionaries is an important record. It contains a list of all members converted in Tranquebar since 27 September 1708.23 The entry of 12 May 1707 particularly contains mention of 102 persons (with six exceptions), with their names, who were already baptized under Christian instruction, together with the dates of their admission and a few notes on their age, relations and their occupations.24

The list presents various kinds of persons such as elderly persons, children, men and women, slaves and freemen, besides those speaking Portuguese and Tamil. Two categories dominated the list. The first included household slaves (the domestic servants) of European families of high rank, especially the Danish officials and Danish pastors in Tranquebar. The second included several foster children of European families. The list refers to three servants of Sigismund Hassius, the Danish Commandant in Tranquebar.25 A female slave of a customs officer had been also mentioned. The female slave of a clergyman’s widow is referred to. The same widow had a criagdo (half-breed in Portuguese language—the Euro-Indian Catholic) girl whom she had brought into the Christian fold.26 It is found that more than 25 per cent are referred to as slave or servant. The distinction between these terms is not clear. Further one notices 8 persons called criagdo and 17 individuals who are children under the age of fourteen, of whom some were foster children. Three members of the same family had been adopted by the Protestant missionaries since they lived in their school. Their father, also a Christian on the list, was unable to care for them. Another child is stated to have been an orphan. One child had been donated by a widow. Thus one finds that slaves had been converted largely to Protestantism in the beginning by the Lutheran missionaries.

Accusation and rumours about the Lutheran missionaries came to be spread widely in Tranquebar since the members of their church were mainly slaves, children and Catholic proselytes. It is reported in a document of 1715 written by a critic of the Danish mission under the pseudonym Christiano Aletophilo which got published much later.27 This remark had already been reflected through the observations of Johann Georg Bovingh, a controversial co-missionary of Ziegenbalg who lived at Tranquebar from July 1709 to August 1711. Among the long list of criticism of the missionary work of Ziegenbalg one finds Bovingh (a tract printed in Europe in 1712), making comments. He stated that the poor and miserable and the defectors from the Roman Church became Christians in Tranquebar.28 It came to be well known in Denmark (through the publication of ‘Christian Friend of Truth’ in 1715) that the Christian population in Tranquebar consisted largely of slaves and former Catholics, poor people and even slave children who had been purchased.29

Ziegenbalg wrote in his letters that many of the Catholic Christians in Tranquebar were natives and they were employed either in the service of the Company, or private servants and slaves of Danish traders.30 The observations of the missionaries also relate a causal connection between poverty, disease and bondage. Many who could not find employment, worn out and sick from hunger and impoverishment, became slaves. Individuals in dire straits and unbearable to bear hunger, delivered either themselves or their families into slavery.31 Ziegenbalg who observed all these various types, therefore began to plead for slave rights and he expressed these in his writings.32

The Lutheran missionaries sought to improve the morals of the slaves by Christianizing them and this was a missionary project. They were strongly egalitarian and their schools took in pupils from all castes in 1729, including both Tamil and Portuguese slaves (a mixed race group that persisted as a classification within the strictly segregated world). One sees paintings of these slaves doing various household work at Tranquebar in 1729 sent by the Lutheran missionaries to Halle and they are preserved at the Francke Foundation Archives.33 On 16 October 1706 Plutschau, the missionary, had asked the people to send the domestic slaves and those slaves employed in the Danish East India Company to the schools which they had opened newly.34 With the large scale mestico population which continued to live in Tranquebar, the missionaries made attempts to improve their lifestyle as they were denied the opportunity to move ahead in life.

The missionary education directing at Tamil slaves, pariaiyars and the Portuguese mixed-race population, supported an argument that highlighted enlightenment against the slave trade. It led to conflicts with both colonial traders and local elite interests, resulting in complaints that the missionaries made slaves stubborn and unmanageable.35

TRANQUEBAR MISSIONARY DESCRIPTIONS
AND DISCUSSIONS ON SLAVERY

Missionaries in Tranquebar began to examine the system of prevalent slavery in depth. They described the major difference of the slavery of the Tamils then practised in Tranquebar to that of the European concept of slavery. The letter of Nikolaus Dal, Christian Friedrich Pressier and Christoph Theodosius Walther, the Protestant missionaries in Tranquebar to Michaelis in Germany dated 12 January 1727 explained it well and referred to a Tamil proverb which stated that a person who was born in one’s household, gets treated like one’s own child. It was mentioned that, according to Tamil law (nach dem Recht der Malabaren) the slave owners were not allowed to sell children of their slaves.36

The Lutheran missionaries in Tranquebar were questioned by the fellow missionaries in Germany. It was asked whether the slave trade had been regarded by Tamils as good. The reply furnished was that slave trade had not at all been considered ethically good by Tamils.37

The missionaries had added that there were mutual obligations between masters and slaves in Tranquebar. When a master was about to die, he called for his slaves who had served than obediently, granted them their freedom and provided them with whatever money might be necessary for their managing and maintaining their households and protected their dignity. If a master had many slaves not only men but also women, he allowed them to marry one another and kept on being a help to them.38

EXPLAINING THE VARIOUS METHODS
OF SLAVE TRAPS

The missionaries mentioned that there were many ways to obtain or buy chattel slaves (leibeigenen) in Tranquebar. A person could approach another with a gush of persuasive words promising him good clothes and that he would drape him with all sorts of ornaments. In order to overcome his hesitation, he spoke to him deceptively. Afterwards he would rendezvous with him in the night, ran away to another place, and gave him a good meal and later he would sell him unscrupulously to others.

The second method was that a person threw a powder on someone to make him go out of his mind. It worked like this a person took a particular type of powder, went to a distant place looked around for potentially good and valuable slaves, sprinkled them with the powder and then backed off. As soon as the powder fell on the person, it made him go so crazy that he searched for the one who sprinkled the powder on him and voluntarily follow him like a fool. When they had gone a good distance, the imposter provided him with food, clothing and whatever else he needed and at last sold him off.

The third method was that some people, not knowing the difference between good and evil and voluntarily sold themselves, and their children also became slaves.39

INTERNAL MIGRATION AND SLAVE EXPORTS
FROM TRANQUEBAR TO ACEH IN SUMATRA
AND CAPE TOWN IN SOUTH AFRICA
IN 1727-1749

Slaves were used mainly in domestic work by the Europeans in Tranquebar. Many native traders exported slaves overseas. The ship Christianus Sextus named after the Danish king, sailed from Tranquebar to Aceh in 1727 and it carried slaves on a Tamil merchant’s account. Ships flying the Danish flag carried slaves to Aceh as slave trade flourished there. Abishegam a Hindu who worked for the Protestant missionaries had been sold as a slave in 1728. He committed a theft in the Danish settlement and as a punishment he was exiled to Aceh in the ship that sailed in 1729.40 In Tranquebar the Danish administration officially allowed the sale of slaves for export overseas.

The internal migration of the people in Tamil country particularly from the region of Ramanathapuram (Maravar country) to the region of Thanjavur took place at that time. It had helped in a large measure to replenish the labour supply and helped to increase agricultural production during 1732-5. Some of these labour migrants to Thanjavur area who could not find adequate means to support themselves, came forward to sell themselves as slaves in Tranquebar. This had been reported by the Lutheran missionaries.41

The Danes and other European residents in Tranquebar purchased and sold slaves to the Dutch Company in Nagapattinam since there was heavy demand. According to missionary records the slave market in Tranquebar after 1729 did not yield any profit. So the Europeans of Tranquebar did not purchase slaves, although a slave could be bought for any amount between two panams and four panams. The main reason was that the slaves purchased did not stay alive owing to sickness and poor health and died very early.42

In November 1730 the missionaries had mentioned the export of slaves from Tranquebar to Cape Town. It has been said that the missionaries had given several Tamil books printed in Tranquebar to a slave to take with him to South Africa.43

Many slaves sold to the Dutch Company in Nagapattinam were taken from Tranquebar.44 Engelbert, a slave was sold and he waited for export to Pegu in Myanmar in 1741. Ignasia, a slave was sold in 1747 and she was exported to Colombo in Sri Lanka. Further, Caesar and Cassander were sold as slaves and they were to be exported to Cape Town in 1747.45 Thus Dutch slave trade at Nagapattinam came to expand through Tranquebar slave supply.

The Lutheran missionaries in Tranquebar were very much opposed to the practice of slavery because slaves exported were Christians to a large extent. Yet they could do very little against slavery and slave trade.46 Export of slaves from Tranquebar to Cape Town had developed directly under the Danes by that time.

According to records, the conversion of slaves by a Protestant missionary in a ship is interesting to note. It has been mentioned that 17 Tamil boys and young men were sold in Tranquebar to be exported to South Africa in 1741. Nine of them were aged between 8 and 12 years, while seven of them were aged between 16 and 19 and one slave was 22 years old. The castes to which they belonged have been mentioned, while 8 of them were paraiyars, 5 were vellalars, 3 were pallis and one slave who spoke Telugu was of an unknown caste.47 All these slaves were transported in a ship in which the Protestant missionary travelled to Copenhagen and in the course of voyage he gave them catechism lessons. It is mentioned that the slaves also wanted to get baptized prior to reaching Cape Town.48

It has also been mentioned by Benjamin Schultze, another Protestant missionary of Tranquebar in his letter from Copenhagen, dated 21 November 1743 to the Tranquebar missionaries, wherein he said that he had arrived safely to Europe but he felt very bad when two slaves of Tranquebar destined for Cape Town were whipped very badly on board the ship in which he travelled to Copenhagen.49 Though trade in slaves had been outlawed by Pratap Singh (1739-63) the Maratha ruler of Thanjavur, the Danes continued to buy slaves who were available and continued to transport them to South Africa.

The letter of the missionaries of Tranquebar to Francke at Halle in Germany dated 20 December 1741 complained that the people from Thanjavur and Ramanathapuram feared to come to Tranquebar and Poraiyar to meet the missionaries. The simple reason was that of the danger of being kidnapped at any time and shipped to Aceh or Cape Town where the slaves were in heavy demand.50 Slaves brought to Aceh in Sumatra were often the children of indebted families.

THE REACTION TO THE DANISH SLAVE TRADE
BY THE KING OF THANJAVUR, 1741-1744

Pratap Singh, the Maratha ruler of Thanjavur did his best since he disliked slave trade of the Europeans in the ports of his kingdom. He was totally against the natives who engaged themselves as slave dealers and brokers for the European companies. It has been mentioned in the missionary records that the slave traders were punished severely in the kingdom of Thanjavur. Muthu Nayakkan the Tamil catechist who travelled from Tranquebar to Puthakudi on 5 September 1741 found a hand hanging from a tree. He came to know on enquiry that it belonged to a convicted slave trader whose hand had been cut off as a punishment. He learnt that the slave trader had finally died of the injury.51

Again, it has been mentioned by Aaron, the Tamil pastor in his report that he saw two former slave dealers/traders on a stake near Kollimangudi on 5 September 1743. They were executed prior to being impaled for display.52 Thus Pratap Singh the Maratha ruler of Thanjavur banned slave trade and exports and took stern measures. Slave traders were seen as malicious scoundrels, rogues and kidnappers and so they were hated, tortured cruelly and punished. Yet many men, women and slave children were traded secretly by the Europeans reaching the ports.

THE PROHIBITION ORDER ISSUED BY THE
DANISH GOVERNOR FOR SLAVE
TRADE IN TRANQUEBAR, 1745

The local Tamil elites in the surrounding villages of Tranquebar were very unhappy when their slaves ran away where the Danish Company gave shelter and refuge. The work of the missionaries also became controversial when Hindu slaves became Christians. Thus, serious conflicts arose between the kingdom of Thanjavur and the Danish administration in Tranquebar. At the same time, it contributed importantly to the formation of discourses of abolition. The Lutheran missionaries lobbied mainly for interventions to restrict the kidnapping and sale of involuntary slaves. The outcome of this necessity was the prohibition of the slave trade in Tranquebar, promulgated by an order by Carsten Carstensen the Danish Governor (1744-6) in 1745.

He issued a public proclamation on 20 July 1745 in Tranquebar prohibiting and abolishing the accustomed trade in slaves. However, it was still allowed to buy slaves for private use, those slaves, who of their own free will and intention sold themselves, or were put up for sale by their real parents.53 The proclamation also made it clear the trade was prohibited in people, who were not already slaves. The purpose of the proclamation is framed in a discourse of evangelical enlightenment, making a reference to both natural law and the rights of people. This was done in order to prevent the trade and enterprise in innocent and freeborn human beings.54 The missionaries made the demand to end the trade in slaves except for the quite legal one, in which natives let themselves be sold as slaves than die of hunger. This was considered an important victory by the missionaries, who continued to be supported and respected as critical observers of inhuman practices allowed in Tranquebar by the Danish Company.55

THE DEVELOPMENT OF ILLEGAL SLAVE
TRADE AFTER THE PROHIBITION, 1745-1753

The proclamation of prohibiting the trading of slaves in Tranquebar was issued when the Danish Company was still a private enterprise. Illegal private trade in slaves had developed after 1745.56 The Lutheran missionaries put pressure on owners of slaves in and around Tranquebar to send their slaves to school and let them be baptized. They argued subsequently that slaves who were Christians could not be sold, especially not to Muslims, which met with local opposition as Muslims offered and paid the best prices.

Europeans in Tranquebar continued to buy and sell slaves to the Dutch in Nagapattinam during 1746-7. It has been stated that the Dutch Company had no qualms about selling fellow Christians into slavery whether they were of Tamil or had mixed Tamil and European background. Lutheran missionaries noticed that many people were simply kidnapped by the slave dealers and brokers and though the Danish administration was officially opposed to such kidnappings, it did not take effective steps to stop the bad practice. The Danish Company trade in other commodities and goods had not been highly successful. It was estimated in 1750 that ten to twelve slaves per year were shipped from Tranquebar to Cape Town the central hub that connected the Indian Ocean and the Atlantic slave trade.57

THE ABOLITION OF SLAVE TRADE AND THE
ORDER ISSUED BY THE DANISH GOVERNOR
IN TRANQUEBAR, 1753

As the slave trade continued to thrive on secretly in Tranquebar, there was a need to proclaim the abolition of the slave trade in 1753. Controversy resulted in a proclamation of abolition at that time and the Danish Company directors in Copenhagen prohibited slave trade as Company trade.58 There was much less missionary work amongst the people in the Portuguese congregation in Tranquebar because the congregation had dwindled and there were no new slaves in Tranquebar who could be baptized. Hans Ernst Bonsack (1746-53) the Danish Governor made every effort to stop the slave trade totally. The abolition also meant that missionaries could no longer be accused of being slave traders.

The Danish Company was taken over by the Danish Crown in 1777, after its monopoly on trade to the Cape and beyond, which had expired in 1772. Trade was liberalized and further proclamations were posted in the Danish colony of Tranquebar as a reminder that the slave trading had been prohibited. The letter by Johann Friedrich Köenig (1741-95) the Lutheran missionary in 1773 had reflected the circumstance under which slaves and slavery prevailed in Tranquebar. He said that it was far more bearable than in West Indies where slavery continued over generations where slaves had to do heavy work in the plantations.59

Slave trade stood condemned by 1780 on humanitarian grounds in the eyes of thoughtful and prominent members of the Danish government. A Lutheran missionary wrote in a letter dated 17 October 1780 that the Hindu slaves who received baptism had been urged to serve their masters even more faithfully.60

TRANQUEBAR BORN SLAVES IN SRI LANKA,
CAPE TOWN, MAURITIUS AND
DENMARK, 1775-1794

A record mentions Joana a manumitted slave who was born in Tranquebar. She was sold to the Dutch in Sri Lanka. She lived there according to records. She was the concubine of the slave Lakij who belonged to Van Hek, the under-surgeon in Galle.61

A woman slave in Tranquebar had become Christian. It is found that a daughter was born in Tranquebar to the slave Aurora on 21 July 1774. She was baptized with the name Maria Magdalena in 1775 by the Moravian missionaries in Tranquebar. She was taken in by the Moravian missionary and went to Denmark with the closing down of the Garden of the Moravians at Tranquebar. She lived at Christianfeld in Denmark.62

Slaves purchased in Tranquebar also came to be exported to Mauritius where there was a demand. Naagan, a Tamil from Tranquebar boarded the ship Beaute in August 1784 and he had later testified that economic distress had forced him to come to Mauritius. He was told that he would be employed as a crew member in Mauritius. But on arrival he was sold at a slave auction in Mauritius to a freeman of Tamil origin who had already settled there.63

Slaves from Tranquebar who reached Cape Town were employed mainly in the households. The data of the privately owned slaves from the household inventories (preserved in the archives of the Master of the Orphan Chamber in Cape Town) shows that there were three male slaves from Tranquebar in 1749. Again it has been found that three male slaves and one female slave from Tranquebar were found between 1750 and 1794.64 Slave trade continued because people tried to profit from the misery of others.

THE GOVERNMENT ORDERS ISSUED ENDING
THE SLAVERY IN TRANQUEBAR, 1783-1790

The government order of forbidding export of slaves from the Danish territory of Tranquebar was issued on 20 June 1783 since many foreigners continued to purchase slaves and exported them. It ordered strictly that no slaves should be exported from the Danish colony.65

Again on 21 June 1783, the Danish Governor found it necessary to issue a decree, prohibiting slave trade and stating that punishment would be meted out to those who took slaves out by sea or by land.66 Like the slave trade, abolition was clearly an ongoing business, it was thus directed more against kidnapping and abductions than against the trade in slaves as such and presupposes a colonial society in which the ownership of slaves as servants was commonplace and where the boundaries between slavery and contractual servitude were fuzzy and negotiable.

The government issued an order on 16 December 1790 in Tranquebar prohibiting slave owners to put their slaves in iron. It was stated that the government would punish unruly slaves according to the law.67

CONCLUSION

It has been observed the emergence of slave trade in Tranquebar under the Danes in the seventeenth century and its abolition at the end of the eighteenth century. Several discourses of abolition had been undertaken in the context of slaves of various types including the bonded labour. However all that had been related to this had been the types of slavery that existed in the region of Tranquebar prior and after the coming of the Danes. The development in slave forms had changed from time to time and it had moved from unfree labour from slavery to indenture linking slave trade from Tranquebar to ports of South East Asia, Sri Lanka, Africa and the Atlantic. One notices multinational dimensions of slavery that had chiefly led to prohibition in 1745 and to the next stage of abolition of slavery in 1753 and finally to the end of the slave trade. The Lutheran missionary enterprises based in the Danish colony of Tranquebar had contributed to the development of ideas of education, enlightenment and natural rights that fed into emerging discourses of abolition of slavery.

NOTES

1. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Tranquebar in Global History, 1620-1801: The Coromandel Coast and Europe in a World Network System, Puducherry, 2020, pp. 13-14.

2. R.C. Temple and Lavinia Mary Anstey, eds., The Life of the Icelander Jon Olafsson Traveller to India, 1622-5, 2 vols., London, 1932, p. 151.

3. Martin Krieger, ‘Danish Shipping and Trade between Tranquebar on the Coromandel Coast of India and South East Asia during the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries’, S. Jeyaseela Stephen, ed., The Indian Trade at the Asian Frontier, New Delhi, 2008, pp. 117- 42, see p. 124.

4. Ole Felbaek, ‘No Ship for Tranquebar for Twenty–nine Years: Or the Art of Survival of a Mid–Seventeenth Century European Settlement in India’, Roderich Ptak and D. Rothermund, eds., Emporia, Commodities and Entrepreneurs in Asian Maritime Trade, c. 1400-1750, Heidelberg, 1991, pp. 29-36.

5. Asta Bredsdorff, Willem Leyels liv og farefulde rejse til Indien, Copenhagen, Museum Tusculanus Forlag, 1999, p. 148.

6. Kay Larsen, Dansk-Ostindiske koloniers historie, Copenhagen, Centralførlaget, 1907.

7. William Foster, English Factories in India: A Calendar of Documents in the India Office, British Museum and Public Relations Office, XIII vols., 1906-27, vol. VI, p. 141.

8. Ibid.

9. Archivo General de Indias (hereafter AGI), Seville, Spain, Filipinas 193, n. 11 (1654-2-6).

10. Rigsarkivet (hereafter RA), København, Danske Kancelli (hereafter DK), B 246.

11. Ibid.

12. Asta Bredsdorff, The Trials and Travels of Willem Leyel: An Account of the Danish East India Company in Tranquebar, 1639-48, Copenhagen: Museum Tusculanum Press, 2009, pp. 148-9.

13. Asta Bredsdorff, Willem Leyels liv og farefulde, p. 149.

14. Mourids Christensen, Skildringer fra et ophold I Ostindien (begyndte I Trankenbar 16.3. 1671) med nogle Portugisiske og Malebariske Gloser, 1672. The text runs thus: Mallebarerne naar dee lider trang for Føde, eller Dyre Aaringer er, Selger di bort till Huem som Köbe vill deris egne bøern, Piger och drenge, ia Manden sin egen Kone naar nøden er størst, och dersom hand endaa fattis selger manden sig selffuer och bageffter, och maa werre Slaffuer och arbeede som andre bæster deris Liffuis tid med Hug och slag, nøgen och suelt uden nogen modsigelße.

15. Anthony Reid, ‘Slavery and Bondage in Early Southeast Asian History’, in Charting the Shape of Early Modern Southeast Asia, Singapore, 2000, pp. 181- 206.

16. Der Königl. Dänischen Missionarien aus Ost–Indien eingesandter ausführlichen Berichten, Von dem Werck ihrs Ams unter den Heyden, angerichteten Schulen und Gemeinen, ereigneten Hindernissen und schweren Umstanden; Beschaffenheit des Malabarischen Heydenthums, gepflogenen brieflicher Correspondentz und mundlchen Unterredungen mit selbigen heyden, Teil 1-9 (Continuationen 1-108), Waiserihaus, Halle, 1710-72 (hereafter HB=Hallesche Berichte), vol. 3, cont., 29, p. 470.

17. Gunnar Olsen, Dansk Ostindien, 1616-1732, in Vore gamle tropenkolonier, ed., Johannes Brøndsted, Copenhagen, Wester-mann, 1952, pp. 207-12.

18. Martin Krieger, Danish Shipping and Trade, p. 131.

19. Heike Liebau, Cultural Encounters in India: The Local Co-workers of the Tranquebar Mission, 18th to 19th Centuries, trs. Rekha V. Rajan, New York, Routledge, 2018, p. 152.

20. Ibid.

21. Ibid., pp. 148-9.

22. Ibid., pp. 148-54.

23. Archiv der Franckesche Stiftungen (hereafter AFSt), Halle, MSS MII A6: 5(3), ‘Register of those persons, who through the proclamation of the Gospel by most gracious order of His Royal Majesty of Denmark and Norway, etc., owing to divine grace have been gathered to our pure Evangelical religion from blind heathenism and partly also from sinister papacy from Anno 1707, 12 May on until now 1708, 27 September and also since until the present day are being instructed in our Jerusalem Church in the Word of God on their salvation by Bartholomaus Ziegenbalg and Heinrich Plutschau, servants of the Divine Word among the heathens at the Jerusalem congregation.’

24. W. Germann, ‘Bartholomaus Ziegenbalg als Bahnbrecher der lutherischen Mission’, Allgemeine Missions-Zeitschrift, vol. X, Giltersloh, C. Bertelsmann, 1883, pp. 529-33. Daniel Jeyaraj, Inkulturation in Tranquebar, Erlangen, Verlag der Ev.-Luth. Mission, 1996, pp. 174, 319.

25. Jorge Simon Izquierdo Doaz, ‘The Trade in Domestic Servants (Morianer) from Tranquebar for Upper Class Danish Homes in the First Half of the Seventeenth Century’, Itinerario, vol. 43, special issue 2, Colonial Entanglements: Cross Roads, Contact Zones and flows in Scandinavian Global History, 2019, pp. 194-217.

26. W. Germann, ‘Bartholomaus Ziegenbalg’, p. 533.

27. Christiano Aletophilo, Kurze und wahrhafte Relation von dem Ursprung und Fortgang der Danisch-Malabarischen Missionariorum, 1715, in J. Ferd Fenger, Geschichte der Trankebarschen Mission, Aus dem Danischen tbersetzt, Grimma, J.M. Gebhardt, 1845, pp. 98, 277.

28. Der Koniglich Danischen Missionariomm unter den Ost-Indischen Heiden abgendtigte Apologia Epistolis Bovingianis, in Niels-Peter Moritzen, ed., Bartholomaus Ziegenbalg, Johannes Ernst Grilndler, Von den Anfangen evangelischer Mission, Zwei unbekannte Missionsschriften von 1713 und 1717, Bonn, Verlag fiir Kultur und Wissenschaft, 2002, pp. 91, 95.

29. E. Arno Lehmann, It Began at Tranquebar: A History of the First Protestant Mission in India, trs. Martin J. Lutz, second edition, Chennai, 2006, pp. 43-4.

30. Arno Lehmann, ed., Alte Briefe aus Indien: Unverdffentlichte Briefe von Bartholomaus Ziegenbalg, 1706-19, Berlin, Evangelische Verlagsanstalt, 1957, p. 83.

31. HB, Cont. 34, p. 1056.

32. Anders Nørgaard, Mission und Obrigkeit: Die Dänisch-Hallische Mission in Tranquebar 1706-1845, Gütersloh, Verlagshaus Gerd Mohn, 1988, pp. 33, 36-8.

33. AFSt, M2 B5: 7. ‘Portugiesische Sklaven die Weitzen mahlen’ and ‘Eine Portugiesche Sklavin die zur Kirchen gehet’.

34. W. Germann, Ziegenbalg und Plutschau. Die Grundungsjahre der Trankebarschen Mission, Erlangen, Andreas Deichert, 1868, p. 15.

35. Gunnar Olsen, Dansk Ostindien. 1616-1732, pp. 231-9; Kamma Struwe, Dansk Ostindien 1732-76: Tranquebar under Kompagnistyre, second edition, Copenhagen, Fremad, 1967, pp. 113-16.

36. AFSt, M1 B3: 26, pp. 1-2.

37. Daniel Jeyaraj and Richard Fox Young (translated, introduced and annotated), Hindu-Christian Epistolary Self-Discourses: ‘Malabarian Correspondence’ between German Pietist Missionaries and South Indian Hindus (1712-14), Harrassowitz Verlag, Wiesbaden, 2013, pp. 268-9.

38. Ibid., pp. 270-1.

39. Ibid.

40. AFSt, M1 F3: 5, p. 7, see, Supplementum Des Verzeichnißes der glieder der Portugiesischen, Malabarischen Stadt-und Land-Gemeine vom 5 October 1728: bis d: 5ten October 1729. Nebst einem anhang von denen die in diesen Jahr abgegangen.

41. HB, vol. 3, cont., 30, pp. 544-5.

42. HB, vol. 3, cont., 28, pp. 366-7. The text runs thus: Einwohner wollen auch keine Sclaven mehr kaufen, ob man gleich einen für 2 bis 4 fanam . . . Denn sie bleiben nicht leben.

43. HB, vol. 3, cont., 31, p. 701.

44. AFSt, M2 C15: 3, p. 5, Supplementum des Verzeichnißes der Glieder der Portugiesischen und Malabarischen Stad-und Land-Gemeine vom 5 October 1740 bis 5 October 1741, Nebst einem Anhang von denen die in diesem Jahr abgegangen.

45. AFSt, M2 C15: 9, p. 15, IItes Supplementum Des Verzeichnisses der Glieder der Portugiesischen u: Tamulischen Stadt-und Land-Gemeine, vom 5ten Octobr 1746, bis 5ten Octobr 1747, Nebst einem Anhange von denen in diesem Jahr abgegangenen.

46. AFSt, M1 B29: 29, p. 2.

47. AFSt, M2 C15: 3, pp. 3, 5.

48. HB, vol. 5, cont., 53, p. 786.

49. AFSt, M1 K5: 14, p. 3.

50. AFSt, M1 B29: 29, p. 2.

51. HB, vol. 5, cont., 54, p. 1003.

52. HB, vol. 5, cont., 60, pp. 1802-3.

53. Kay Larsen, ‘Danmark og Slavehandelens Ophævelse’, Historisk Tidsskrift, vol. X, no. 4, 1937, pp. 106-8; Martin Krieger, Der dänische Sklavenhandel auf dem Indischen Ozean im 17. und 18. Jahrhundert, Jahrbuch für Europäische Überseegeschichte vol. XII, 2012, pp. 9-30, see p. 21.

54. Kay Larsen, ‘Danmark og Slavehandelens Ophævelse’, p. 107.

55. Anders Nørgaard, Mission und Obrigkeit, pp. 159-61.

56. Martin Krieger, Der dänische Sklavenhandel, pp. 21-2.

57. Kamma Struwe, Dansk Ostindien 1732-76, pp. 59-64.

58. Søren Mentz, ‘Handelsstationen Tranquebar, 1630-1750’, in Danmark og Kolonierne Indien: Tranquebar, Serampore og Nicobarerne, ed. Niels Brimnes, Copenhagen, Gads Forlag, 2017, pp. 76-111, see p. 109.

59. Heike Liebau, Cultural Encounters, p. 154.

60. Ibid., pp. 154-5.

61. Sri Lanka National Archives (hereafter SLNA), Colombo, Dutch Central Government of Coastal Ceylon, 1640-1796, 1/4740, 1/4702, Criminal dossiers, fls.31r–v, Articles 1 and 2.

62. Unitats Archive (hereafter UA), Herrnhut, R.22.84.21. The Biography of Maria Magdalena Malabar. It is stated that she died on 10 May 1827.

63. Marina Carter, Veils from Indenture: Experiences of Indian Migrants in the British Empire, London, 1996, p. 92.

64. Nigel Worden, ‘Indian Ocean Slaves in Cape Town, 1695-1805’, Journal of South African Studies, 42(3), 2016, pp. 389-408, see p. 406.

65. Calendar Containing Notifications (1779-1824) Issued by the Administration at Tranquebar 1779, Danish Records, Serial No. 1, Government Press, Madras, 1908, p. 4.

66. Georg Christian Knapp et. al., Neuere Geschichte der Evangelischen Missions-Anstalten zu Bekehrung der Heiden in Ostindien, Waisenhaus, Halle 1770-8/95, 1848, 29. St, 531.

67. Calendar Containing Notification, p. 6.